瓦雷利亚末日
伊耿一世（AC1-37 在位）
“征服者”
镶嵌红宝石的瓦雷利亚钢王冠
坦格利安家族征服维斯特洛
雷妮丝
伊耿一世的妹妹和妻子
伊尼斯一世（AC37-42 在位）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
亚莉珊（AC36-100）
“善良王后”
杰赫里斯一世的妹妹和妻子
贝尔隆（AC57-101）
“勇敢的”“春晓王子”
杰赫里斯一世的儿子和国王之手
阿莱莎（AC60-84）
贝尔隆的妹妹和妻子
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
兰娜尔·瓦列利安
科利斯和雷妮丝的女儿 戴蒙的妻子
雷妮拉
韦赛里斯一世的女儿和王储
瓦列利安家族参加王室婚礼
改编自 《血与火：坦格利安王朝史》
[美] 乔治·马丁 著
龙 王 家 族
第一季 第六集
公主与王后 The Princess and the Queen
雷妮拉·坦格利安
“王国之光” 龙石岛公主 王储
保持呼吸
Keep breathing.
用力
And push.
再来一次
And again.
我做不到
I can't.
用力！
Push!
头出来了！
The head!
是个男孩 公主殿下
A boy, Princess.
赞美圣母！
Praise the Mother!
健康吗？
Healthy?
踢得像山羊一样有力 公主殿下
Kicking like a goat, Princess.
公主殿下……
Princess...
王后要求把孩子带去见她……
the Queen has requested that the child be brought to her...
现在就要
immediately.
为什么？
Why?
我自己带他去
I'll take him myself.
您应该卧床休养 公主殿下——
You should remain abed, Princess--
是 我是该躺着！帮我更衣
Yes, I should! Help me dress.
殿下……
Princess...
换一下裙子？
your dress?
公主殿下？
Princess?
- 它出来了 - 胎盘！
-It's coming. -The afterbirth!
兰尼诺·瓦列利安
科利斯与雷妮丝·坦格利安之子
是个男孩 我刚听说了
A boy. I've just heard.
- 是的 - 干得好
-Yes. -Well done.
- 你去哪儿？ - 她想看他
-Where are you going? -She wants to see him.
现在？
Now?
我跟你一起去
I'm coming with you.
- 我也觉得 - 让我抱着他
-I should hope so. -Let me take him.
不行 她休想看我的笑话
No, she'll get no such satisfaction from me.
不管怎样 还是扶着我的胳膊吧
Just take my arm, at the least.
疼得特别厉害吗？
Was it terribly painful?
七神啊
Oh gods.
我曾被长枪刺穿过肩膀
I took a lance through the shoulder once.
我深表同情
My deepest sympathies.
公主殿下…… 公主殿下……
The Princess... The Princess...
我真庆幸自己不是女人
I am glad I am not a woman.
- 公主殿下…… - 大人……
-My Princess... -My Lord...
怎么了？
What is it?
怎么了？出什么事了？
What is it? What is it?
操
Fuck.
走 快走！
Walk. Walk!
她到底想干嘛？
What could she possibly want?
我以为这事已经翻篇了
I thought we were past this.
公主殿下 兰尼诺爵士 很荣幸
Princess, Ser Laenor, it is a privilege
能成为第一批向您道喜的人
to be amongst the first to congratulate you.
谢谢你 卡斯威大人
Thank you, Lord Caswell.
如果我能帮上您的忙
If I may be of any service.
总有这么一天的 大人
The day may yet come, my Lord.
我们这就回去 好吗？
We are turning back, all right?
她可以来找我们 对吧？
She can come to us, all right?
不 除非你想把我扛下那该死的台阶
No. Not unless you wish to carry me down those fucking stairs.
这真荒唐
This is absurd.
克里斯顿·科尔
御林铁卫
公主殿下
Princess.
阿莉森·海塔尔
王后 奥托之女
雷妮拉！你刚生完孩子 应该好好休息
Rhaenyra! You should be resting after your labors.
我相信这是您的真心话 陛下
I have no doubt that you would prefer that, Your Grace.
你得坐下来
You must sit.
塔雅 给公主拿个靠垫来
Talya, fetch a cushion for the Princess.
- 没有这个必要 - 别犟了
-There's no need. -Nonsense.
我们等下再谈
We'll finish this later.
陛下
Your Grace.
大早上的这是什么好消息
What happy news this morning.
韦赛里斯·坦格利安一世
国王
的确 陛下
Indeed, Your Grace.
他人呢？
Where is he?
我的外孙在哪儿？这儿呢
Where is my grandson? There.
他在这呢
There he is.
好王子
A fine Prince.
很结实
Sturdy.
你会成为一名令人生畏的骑士
You will make a fearsome knight.
是的 你会的
Yes, you will.
孩子取名字了吗？
Does the babe have a name yet?
我们还没谈——
We haven't spoken--
乔佛里
Joffrey.
他叫乔佛里
He'll be called Joffrey.
这名字对瓦列利安家族来说真是少见呢
That's an unusual name for a Velaryon.
他的鼻子真是像了他爸爸
I do believe he has his father's nose.
不是吗？
Don't you?
如果您不介意的话 陛下
If you don't mind, Your Grace,
您的女儿表现英勇 现在该休息了
your daughter has exerted herself heroically and should rest.
那是当然
Of course.
给
There.
干得漂亮 我的女儿
Well done, my girl.
我真的希望分娩顺利
I do hope the labor was easy.
我想我管产婆叫婊子来着
I think I called the midwife a cunt.
继续努力吧 兰尼诺爵士
Do keep trying, Ser Laenor.
迟早会有个长得像你的孩子
Soon or late, you may get one who looks like you.
你不觉得给我的孩子取名字之前最好问问我吗？
You don't think to consult me before you name my child?
他是我们的孩子 不是吗？
He's our child, is he not?
咱俩之间可只有一个人流血了
Only one of us is bleeding.
我对自己的家事应该是有发言权的吧
I deserve some say in the affairs of my own family.
你最近可是对我们的家事没什么兴趣呢
You haven't seemed so interested in our affairs of late.
然后他看见了一条可怕的巨龙！
And he sees a big, scary dragon!
哈尔温·斯壮
“碎骨人” 莱昂诺的长子 都城守备队长
母亲……
Mother...
看
look.
杰卡里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的长子
路斯里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的次子
我们给娃娃选了一颗龙蛋
We chose an egg for the baby.
看上去真合适
That looks like the perfect one.
- 我让小路去选的 - 谢谢你 小杰
-I let Luke choose. -Thank you, Jace.
不是每天都有龙蛋能带出龙穴的 公主
Not every day an egg leaves the Dragonpit, Princess.
所以我护送孩子们过来
I thought it best to escort the lads.
兰尼诺和我谢谢你 队长
Laenor and I thank you, Commander.
又是个男孩 我听说
Another boy, I heard.
你将来成了骑士 得多优秀啊 嗯？
What a fine knight you are going to make, eh?
我可以吗？
Might I?
哈尔温爵士希望见见乔佛里
Ser Harwin wishes to be introduced to Joffrey.
当然
Of course.
叫乔佛里 是吧？
Joffrey, is it?
父亲 我可以抱抱乔佛里吗 拜托？
Father, please may I hold Joffrey?
不 不 不可以
No, no. No.
你们两个 回去龙穴
Back to the Dragonpit for you two.
- 拜托！ - 趁他们还没派人找你们
-Come on! -Before they send out a search party.
你在都城守备队队长面前睡得那么熟
You're asleep in front of the Commander of the City Watch.
太不尊重人了
Terrible lack of respect.
恐怕这种傲慢无礼是家族传统吧
A certain insolence runs in the family, I'm afraid.
等等！
Umbās.
让他过来
伊耿·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的长子
伊蒙德·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的次子
让沃马克斯乖乖听话 杰卡里斯王子
Call Vermax to heel, Prince Jacaerys.
听话！
Dohaerās!
停下！
Kelīs!
做得好
沃马克斯！
Vermax!
停下！
Kelīs!
Zaldrizo aoho syt aeksio sagon ao bevilza,
darilaros nuhys--
你必须好好控制你的龙 我的小王子
You must hold mastery over your dragon, my young Princes.
...hae Darilarot Aegot Vvsperzomy.
就像伊耿王子对阳炎那样
As Prince Aegon has with Sunfyre.
Zijosy aot tetiri ozlettosy,
toli rybagon zirylo vindilza.
一旦和你心灵相连 他们便会拒绝
Once they're fully bound to you, they will refuse
其他任何人发出的指令
to take instruction from any other.
我能说吗？
Can I say it?
龙焰 沃马克斯！
Dracarys, Vermax!
伊蒙德 我们为你准备了一个惊喜
Aemond, we have a surprise for you.
- 是什么？ - 非常特别的东西
-What is it? -Something very special.
咱们就你没龙
You're the only one of us without a dragon.
确实
Indeed.
我们感到很遗憾
And we felt badly about it,
于是为你找了一只
so we found one for you.
龙？怎么可能？
A dragon? How?
七神给予
The gods provide.
- 看哪 - 粉死神！
-Behold-- -The Pink Dread!
一定要小心骑上她
Be sure to mount her carefully.
第一次上天总是很难
First flight's always rough.
这只有60节
This one has 60 rings...
每节有两对足
and two pairs of legs on each.
总共就是240
That's 240.
海伦娜·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的女儿
是的
Yes, it is.
它有眼睛……
It has eyes...
然而……
though...
我觉得它看不见
I don't believe it can see.
你觉得这是为什么呢？
And why is that so, do you think?
这超出了我们的认知
It is beyond our understanding.
我想你是对的 有些事情就是这样
I suppose you're right. Some things just are.
陛下
Your Grace.
伊蒙德
Aemond.
- 你干嘛了？ - 他又去了
-What have you done? -He did it again.
警告过你多少次了
After how many times you've been warned,
非得让我把你锁在房间里吗？！
must I have you confined to your chambers?!
- 他们逼我这么做的！ - 说得好像你需要别人督促一样
-They made me do it! -As if you needed encouragement.
你对那些畜生的痴迷真让人难以置信
Your obsession with those beasts goes beyond understanding.
他们给了我一头猪！
They gave me a pig!
一头什么？
A what?
他们声称找了一条龙给我
They said they found a dragon for me.
最后一节没长腿
The last ring has no legs at all.
但那是一头猪
But it was a pig.
总有一天你会有条龙
You will have a dragon one day.
- 他得闭上一只眼 - 我知道
-He'll have to close an eye. -I know it.
他们全都在笑我
They all laughed.
很明显 他们给猪身上装了翅膀 还有条尾巴
They made wings for it, apparently, and a tail.
小家伙不该轻信他人
The lad shouldn't have been so credulous.
他还是个孩子
He's a child.
他以为他们碰巧遇上了条无主野龙
He thought they'd happened upon some wild unnamed dragon
还把它引来龙穴？
and lured it to the Dragonpit?
是您的外孙干的好事
Your grandsons are a menace.
他们比伊蒙德还小呢
They're more children than he is.
他们是野孩子 没什么可奇怪的
They're savages. And it's not surprising.
你确定不是我们的伊耿撺掇的吗？
Are you sure it wasn't our Aegon who put them up to it?
他们的龙蛋能孵化 简直是奇迹
It's a wonder to me their eggs ever hatched.
- 为什么这么说？ - 您明白为什么
-And why is that? -You know why.
- 恐怕我不明白 - 别装了！
-I'm afraid I don't. -Don't!
韦赛里斯
Viserys.
艾德 我们今天下午继续
We shall continue this afternoon, Eddard.
我曾向您提过此事
I have raised this matter before
因为您不让我说 所以我闭口不谈
and you forbade me to speak of it, so I held my tongue.
那样的孩子 生一个是犯错
To have one child like that is a mistake,
生了三个就是侮辱
to have three is an insult,
侮辱了王座 您 和瓦列利安家族
to the throne, to you, to House Velaryon
还有您千辛万苦为她找到的对象
and the match you battled so hard to make for her.
更别提做人的体面了
Not to mention decency itself.
我养过一匹黑色的母马
I had a black mare once.
黑如渡鸦
Black like a raven.
突然有一天 她逃离了牧场
One day, she escaped her pasture
附近的公马在她身上下了种
and the neighboring stallion sired a foal on her.
公马是银白色的 宛如冬夜的月光
The stallion was as silver as the moon on a winter's night
至于小马驹 它出生后
and the foal, when it was born,
却是栗色的
chestnut.
就像是你曾见过的最不起眼的棕马
Just the most unremarkable brown horse you ever saw.
大自然的伟力神秘莫测
Nature is a thing of mysterious works.
您怎么确信？
How do you know?
那匹银色公马
The silver stallion.
您怎么能确定就是他？
How do you know it was him?
难道您亲眼见证了他们交配？
Did you witness the act itself?
由你随意的指控
The consequences
导致的结果
of an allegation like the one you toy at
会非常严重
would be dire.
别再提此事了
Do not speak of this again.
难道是我失去理智了吗，科尔爵士？
Have I lost my sanity, Ser Criston?
是我的感性让我误入歧途？
Do my senses lead me astray?
还是所有人都睡着了 做着同一个糊涂梦？
Or is everyone else asleep, dreaming the same woolly dream?
有时候或许是这样的 王后陛下
Sometimes seems so, Your Grace.
她不知羞耻地炫耀自己身为继承人的特权
She flaunts the privilege of her inheritance without shame.
她指望着红堡里的每个人都否认真相
She expects everyone in the Red Keep to deny the truth
否认每一双眼睛明白看到的事实
our eyes can all plainly see.
- 至于国王 她的父亲 - 他知情
-And the King, her father-- -He knows.
他当然知道
Of course, he knows.
至少曾经知道 可他说服了自己
Or did once, but has convinced himself otherwise.
只会为她找借口
He'll do naught but make excuses for her.
雷妮拉公主厚颜无耻 冷酷无情
The Princess Rhaenyra is brazen and relentless.
就像蜘蛛 刺了猎物后吸食得干干净净
A spider who stings and sucks her prey dry.
她就是个被宠坏了的贱逼
A spoiled cunt.
是我僭越了 王后陛下 我道歉
That was beneath me, Your Grace. I apologize.
我必须相信
I have to believe,
到头来 荣誉和体面会占上风
that in the end, honor and decency will prevail.
我们需要坚持这一点 对待彼此也是这样
We need to hew to that and to each other.
谁出的主意？
Whose idea was it?
那头猪
The pig.
是你搞的吗？
Was it your plot?
不……
No...
是小杰和……
it was Jace and...uh...
就……就是他俩
it...it was the two of them.
我不确定是哪个
I couldn't be sure.
伊蒙德是你弟弟
Aemond is your brother.
- 呃 他也是个傻逼 - 我们是一家人
-Well, he's a twat. -We are family.
你在家里可以铐着他 任由你随心所欲
You may cuff him about as you wish at home,
但在外边 我们必须保护自己人
but in the world, we must defend our own.
挺好笑的
It was funny.
你认为雷妮拉的儿子们会永远被你玩弄于手掌心吗？
Do you think Rhaenyra's sons will be your playthings forever?
就当前情况而言……
As things stand...
雷妮拉会登上王位 那时杰卡里斯·坦格利安就会是她的继承人
Rhaenyra will ascend the throne and Jacaerys Targaryen will be her heir.
- 所以呢？ - 你都快成年了
-So? -You are nearly a man-grown.
怎么眼界还这么短浅？
How is it that you can be so shortsighted?
一旦雷妮拉掌权……
If Rhaenyra comes into power...
你很有可能没命
your very life could be forfeit.
伊蒙德同样如此
Aemond's as well.
她会除掉对她继承大统的威胁
She could move to cut off any challenge to her succession.
那我不威胁不就——
Then I won't challenge--
你本身就是威胁！
You are the challenge!
你本身就是威胁 伊耿！
You are the challenge, Aegon!
只要你活着 还能喘气
Simply by living and breathing!
你是国王的长子
You are the King's firstborn son
他们知道 全天下人都知道
and what they know, what everyone in the realm knows
在他们深入骨髓的观念里……
in their blood and in their bones...
总有一天 你会成为我们的王
is that one day, you will be our King.
把衣服穿上
Get dressed.
科拉克休
戴蒙的龙
戴蒙·坦格利安
“浪荡王子” 韦赛里斯的弟弟
瓦格哈尔
兰娜尔·瓦列利安的龙
兰娜尔·瓦列利安
科利斯与雷妮丝·坦格利安之女 戴蒙的妻子
龙焰！
Dracarys!
羊心非常美味
The lamb hearts are excellent.
我们很幸运有好厨子 英主
We are fortunate in our cook, Your Excellence.
还有一道梅子蛋糕没上来
There's a plum-cake yet to be served,
相信美味到我们会为碎屑打起来
which will have us fighting over the crumbs.
那在我们打起来之前……
Then before we come to blows...
先为征服者伊耿干一杯 敬您崇高的祖先
a toast to Aegon the Conqueror, your exalted forebear,
他在流血世纪加入了我们对抗瓦兰提斯的大业
who joined our cause against Volantis in the Century of Blood.
他骑着巨龙贝勒里恩 飞到里斯来援助我们
On the great dragon Balerion, he flew to our aid in Lys
他烧毁了敌军的舰队 力挽狂澜
and burned a fleet of enemy ships, thus turning the tide.
- 敬征服者伊耿 - 敬伊耿
-Aegon the Conqueror. -To Aegon.
这就引出了另一个话题
This brings me to some business.
我有个提议
A proposal I wish to make
本着尊重我们双方传奇之盟的精神
in the spirit of honoring our storied alliance.
如果想娶我们的哪个女儿 英主
If your aim is to marry one of our daughters, Your Excellence,
您可以直说 不必给我们上历史课
you might have said so and spared us the history lesson.
什么？
What?
我不认为自己能配得上您的女儿 兰娜尔夫人
I would not count myself so deserving, my Lady Laena.
我是想为您在潘托斯提供一处永久住所
I wish to offer you a permanent residence here in Pentos.
把这所宅子直接送给您
This manse I would gift to you, outright,
连带着农庄和土地
along with its farms and lands,
还有葡萄园和林地
the vineyard and the wood.
佃户每年都会缴纳赋税
The tenants would pay their tributes annually
给新的坦格利安领主
to their new Targaryen lord.
您还可以在城市和港口自由出入
You would have your freedom of the city and the harbor,
以彰显您的王家地位
as befits your royal station.
我听着呢
Continue.
里斯及其盟友卷土重来
Lys and its allies rise again.
三城同盟会和多恩的科奥伦·马泰尔结盟
The Triarchy has made common cause with Qoren Martell of Dorne.
他们随时都有可能将目光转向北方
At any moment, they may turn their sights north.
您家里有龙
Your family has dragons.
现在有三只 或许以后还有第四只
Three now, mayhaps four in the future.
我的目的是从三城同盟会的贪欲中保护潘托斯
My aim is to protect Pentos from the lustful eye of the Triarchy.
就像当年伊耿那样援助潘托斯……
Aid Pentos in this, as Aegon once did...
我的感激将盈满您的酒杯 多到盛不下
and my gratitude will fill your cup and overflow it.
英主 我们只是旅人
Your Excellence, we are travelers.
我们在此地已经停留得够久了
We've already extended our visit here.
您的馈赠非常慷慨
It's a most generous offer.
我们一定会加以考虑
And one we will certainly entertain.
你在考虑雷吉奥亲王的提议
You are considering Prince Reggio's offer.
我们在这儿生活得很好
We have a good life here.
自由自在 还受到热情款待
We're free to do as we please, welcomed and feted.
- 作为永远的客人 - 正是
-And eternally guests. -Precisely.
不需背负责任 无论是政治权谋
We are without responsibility. The political scheming,
还是反复无常的效忠对象或继承人
the endless shifting of loyalties and succession
这些事情都与我们无关
is none of ours.
- 他们在利用我们 - 真是新鲜事 对吧？
-They are using us. -It's refreshing, isn't it?
一笔简单的交易
A simple transaction.
我们有龙 他们有金子
We have dragons, they have gold.
我们远不止于此 戴蒙
We are more than this, Daemon.
我们不是吟游诗人或者戏子
We are not minstrels or mummers
只为博取某位异国亲王的欢心而表演
who play at the pleasure of an alien prince.
我们的身上流淌着古瓦雷利亚的血脉
We are the blood of Old Valyria.
这儿不是我们的家
We don't belong here.
瓦雷利亚早就没了 哪儿都不是我们的家
Valyria is gone. We don't belong anywhere.
我希望把孩子生在我出生的地方 生在潮头岛上
I want my child to be born where I was born, on Driftmark,
在我父亲大人的城堡里
in my lord father's castle.
我希望我的女儿在她们的故乡长大
I want my daughters to be raised in their homeland
与亲人在一起 这是她们天生的权利
with their family according to their birthright.
在我生命终结的时候 我希望作为驭龙者死去
And at my end, I want to die a dragonrider's death.
而不是什么乡下的胖贵族
Not that of some fat country lord.
膝盖要放松
Soften your knees.
脚步要轻盈
Feet light.
脚要轻手要重
Keep your feet light and your hands heavy.
莱昂诺·斯壮
国王之手
就是这样啊 莱昂诺
This is the stuff, Lyonel.
一起学习一起训练的小伙子们
Lads that learn together, train together...
打倒对方 又扶他起来
knock each other down, pick each other up.
当然会形成一辈子的牵绊 不是吗
They will certainly form a lifelong bond, wouldn't you agree?
希望如此 陛下
That is the hope, Your Grace.
别站得那么直 王子 会被打倒的
Don't stand too upright, my Prince. You'll get knocked down.
伊耿
Aegon.
我赢得了第一场比赛 克里斯顿爵士
I've won my first bout, Ser Criston.
我的对手求饶了
My opponent sues for mercy.
那就给你来个新对手 我的稻草人大人
You'll have a new opponent then, My Lord of the Straw.
来看看你能不能碰到我
Let's see if you can touch me.
你和你弟弟一起上
You and your brother.
还得努力啊
You're gonna have to do better than that.
举起武器 孩子们
Weapons up, boys.
不要对敌人心慈手软
Give your enemies no quarter.
看样子你多给点关注的话
It seems the younger boys could do better with a bit
这些小男孩们能练得更好 克里斯顿爵士
of your attention, Ser Criston.
你是在质疑我的教学方法吗 爵士？
You question my method of instruction, ser?
我只是建议你对所有学生都用上这些方法
I merely suggest that method be applied to all your pupils.
好吧
Very well.
杰卡里斯 过来
Jacaerys, come here.
你和伊耿对练
You spar with Aegon.
长子对长子
Eldest son against eldest son.
- 这不公平吧 - 我知道你从未见过
-It's hardly a fair match. -I know you've never seen
真正的战场 爵士 但是白刃相向之际
true battle, ser, but when steel is drawn,
就没人能奢求公平了
a fair match isn't something anyone should expect.
举剑
Blades up.
开打
Engage.
- 犯规 - 我来处理
-Foul play. -I'll deal with him.
扎稳脚跟 你重心低是个优势
Plant your feet. You have a height advantage.
利用这一点 向他逼近……
Use it. Advance on him...
上啊！
You!
逼紧
Close with him.
逼他退后！逼紧！
Press him backward! Close with him!
持续进攻！用脚！
Stay on the attack! Use your feet!
不要让他爬起来
Don't let him get up.
保持进攻！
Stay on the attack!
够了！
Enough!
- 你怎么敢碰我？ - 伊耿！
-You dare put hands on me? -Aegon!
你失礼了 斯壮 这是王子殿下
You forget yourself, Strong. That is the Prince.
这就是你的教学吗 科尔？
This is what you teach, Cole?
残酷地……
Cruelty...
对待更弱小的对手？
to the weaker opponent?
你对王子们训练的关心程度很不寻常啊 队长
Your interest in the princeling's training is quite unusual, Commander.
大多数人只会以这样的热情
Most men would only have that kind of devotion
去关心自己的表兄弟……
toward a cousin...
或是兄弟……
or a brother...
或是儿子
or a son.
后退！
Get back!
你再说一遍！
Say it again!
再说一遍！
我猜就是
Thought as much.
拿块浴巾给他洗澡
Let him be bathed with a cloth,
然后让厨师
and see to it the cook
给你一杯清澈的好酒
gives you a good, clear wine to drink.
公主殿下……
Princess...
训练场上出了点事故
there's been an incident in the yard.
这让我时刻感到羞耻
It fills me with unrelenting shame.
所以你就是为了这个？
So that's what this is about then?
你的耻辱
Your shame.
我们的耻辱 哈尔温！
Our shame, Harwin!
整个斯壮家族的耻辱
Shame on the whole of House Strong.
因为我对那个让人无法忍受的科尔出手了？
Because I laid my hands on that insufferable Cole,
- 不就是个管家的儿子？ - 他现在是御林铁卫的骑士
-the son of a steward? -He is a Knight of the Kingsguard now,
- 是王家护卫 - 他攻击了杰卡里斯王子
-a defender of the crown. -He assailed Prince Jacaerys,
王位未来的继承人
the future heir to the throne.
而你使我们面临的指控
You have laid us open to accusations
是更加丑陋的背叛
of an uglier treachery.
什么背叛？
And what treachery is that?
别跟我装傻 小子
Don't play the fool with me, boy.
你和雷妮拉公主的亲密关系
Your intimacy with the Princess Rhaenyra
是会导致流放和死亡的罪行……
is an offense that would mean exile and death...
不论是你 还是她 还是孩子们！
for you, for her, for the children!
这只是谣言……
It is rumor only...
是公主的对手散播的
spun by the Princess's rivals.
大家都有眼睛 孩子
People have eyes, boy.
然而国王陛下看起来似乎不愿意接受他的眼睛看见的东西
Yet His Grace the King, it seems, will not accept what his eyes see.
你和刽子手之间只隔着这么薄薄的一面盾
This flimsy shield alone stands between you and the headsman.
一个父亲对孩子执拗的盲目
The willful blindness of a father towards his child.
希望我的父亲也有同样的盲目
I wish my father affected a similar blindness.
这么多年来难道我没有吗？
Have I not these many years?
然而今天 你公开袭击
And yet today, you publicly assaulted
一位御林铁卫 为了维护你的——
a Knight of the Kingsguard in the, in the defense of your--
您有您的荣誉 我也有我的
You have your honor and I have mine.
这是镇痛的 公主
To ease the pain, Princess.
- 谢谢 - 过两天就会好多了
-Thank you. -You'll feel better in a day or two,
等奶水都回完了
when the milk dries up.
我亲爱的妻子
My dear wife.
公主
Princess.
我摔倒了
I fell down.
- 你去哪了 - 和卡尔一起出去了 我没说吗？
-Where have you been? -Out with Qarl. Didn't I mention it?
你很痛吗？
Are you in very much pain?
奶水……
The milk...
- 会使胸部肿胀—— - 劳驾 卡尔爵士
-swells the breasts-- -Would you mind, Ser Qarl?
我想和丈夫说说话
I would like to speak with my husband.
当然 公主殿下
Of course, Princess.
石阶列岛又要打仗了 雷妮拉
War is afoot again in the Stepstones, Rhaenyra.
三城同盟会和多恩结盟后如获新生
The Triarchy takes new life from its alliance with Dorne.
他们在拦截船只和货物
They're waylaying ships and cargo.
卡尔在那里打过仗 他给我看——
Qarl's been fighting there. He showed me a--
他给我看了一袋子核桃那么大的蓝宝石
He showed me a sack of sapphires big as walnuts
他从砍杀的海盗那里拿的
he took from the pirate he slew.
这么多年了 这正是我需要的啊
after all this time, this is just what I need,
一点点冒险
a little adventure.
一场酣畅淋漓的战斗使我重燃热血
A good, honest battle to enliven my blood again.
他说那里有个泰洛西将军
He says there is a Tyroshi general there,
他们说那是个巨人
a giant, they say,
把胡子染成紫色 还穿着女人的罩袍
who dyes his beard purple and wears women's frocks.
也许过几个月……
A few months, maybe...
就能回到大海上
To be back at sea.
你疯了吗？
Are you mad?
你知道发生了什么吗……
Do you know what's happened...
当你在跳蚤窝畅饮麦酒
while you've been guzzling all the ale in Flea Bottom?
或者天知道还在作什么的时候？
Gods know what besides?
黑暗的谣言在围猎我们 兰尼诺
Dark rumors are hunting us, Laenor.
啃噬我们的脚跟
They nip at our heels.
质疑我们儿子的出身
Questions about our sons' parentage.
卑鄙恶心的含沙射影
Vile, disgusting insinuations.
含沙射影 是吗？
Insinuations, are they?
他们是我们的儿子
They are our sons!
你和我的
Yours and mine.
他们真正的父亲不会在此时抛下他们
And their true father will not abandon them now
去喝遍狭海 挥舞着佩剑
to go carousing through the Narrow Sea, waggling his sword
- 跟水手眉目传情 - 我是个骑士……
-and winking at his sailors. -I am a knight...
也是个战士
and a warrior.
我忠实地扮演自己的角色
And I have played my part here, faithfully...
已经十年了
for 10 years.
- 你们欠我—— - 什么都不欠你！
-I am owed some-- -You are owed nothing!
十年来 你在宫廷里放纵
For 10 years, you have indulged yourself at court,
买最好的马
bought the finest horses,
喝最珍稀的酒
drunk the rarest of wines,
操最浪荡的男孩
fucked the lustiest boys.
这是我们的协议 我对这些没有意见
This was our agreement. I have not begrudged you.
但是……
But...
当风暴来袭时你不能抛弃岗位
you do not desert your post when the storm lashes.
明智的水手会趁风暴汇聚的时候逃走
The wise sailor flees the storm as it gathers.
那好吧 我命令你
Very well then. I command you.
作为公主和王储
As your Princess and the heir to the throne,
我命令你待在君临
you are commanded to remain
待在我身边
in King's Landing and at my side.
已经八年了 亲爱的
It's been eight years, sweetling.
雷妮亚·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的双胞胎次女
- 有半数龙蛋是不会的 你知道吗？ - 不会什么？
-Half of them never do, you know? -What?
孵化
Hatch.
他们会让我也留下么？
Will they let me stay?
“他们”是谁？
Will who let you stay?
潘托斯亲王
The Prince of Pentos.
我没明白
I don't understand.
他想要你和父亲……
He wants you and father...
还有贝妮拉……
and Baela...
因为你们有龙
'cause you have dragons.
和龙建立牵绊的方法不止一种
There is more than one way to bind yourself to a dragon.
我直到15岁才有了龙
I was without one until I was 15 years old
而现在我骑着瓦格哈尔 全世界最大的龙
and now I ride Vhagar, the largest in the world.
你要走的路会困难一些
You have a harder road.
贝妮拉的龙在她出生后不久就孵化了
Baela's dragon was born to her.
但如果你想骑龙
But if you wish to be a rider,
就要去自己争取
you must claim that right.
你父亲也会这样跟你讲的
Your father would tell you the same.
父亲不理我
Father ignores me.
他已经尽力了
He's doing his best.
兰尼诺来信了
Laenor has written.
雷妮拉又生了个儿子
Rhaenyra has delivered another son.
那你哥哥有没有说这孩子
Does your brother mention if this one
也特别像都城守备队队长
also bears a marked but entirely coincidental
但纯属巧合？
resemblance to the Commander of the City Watch?
他似乎略掉了这个细节
He seems to have left that detail out.
我想我哥哥了 戴蒙
I miss my brother, Daemon.
你应该也很思念哥哥吧
As I think do you.
我思念维斯特洛的烈酒
I miss Westerosi strongwine.
足以让人安详地淡忘好几个时辰
It could be depended on for a few hours of peaceful oblivion.
这里的人只喝琥珀色的猫尿
This amber shit that they drink here.
你难道不想家么？
Do you never long for home?
不想
No.
-我才不信呢 -信不信随你咯
-I don't believe you. -Believe what you please.
你赞美潘托斯的优点 却对它毫无兴趣
You laud the virtues of Pentos, but you have no interest in it.
你要真喜欢潘托斯 早就去城里游历了 但结果呢
If you did, you would venture into the city, but instead,
你在图书室里打发时间 一遍遍地翻阅
you spend your time here, in the library, reading accounts
那些逝去的龙王的故事 还声称他们的遗产不会束缚你
of the same dead dragonlords whose legacy you claim has no hold on you.
没想到还有人在时时刻刻监督我啊
Didn't know I was being so minutely observed.
你都不睡觉
You do not sleep.
唔 你总这么守着我我哪睡得着呢
Well, how can I with you haunting my every move?
我知道你的人生被辜负了
Life has, I know, disappointed you.
可能我也辜负了你吧 不是你想要的妻子
Perhaps, I too, am not the wife you would've wished for yourself.
兰娜尔
Laena.
我并不为此难过
It does not pain me.
我已经放宽心态了
I have made my peace.
但你不该止步于此 戴蒙
But you are more than this, Daemon.
我嫁的男人过去不会止步于此
The man I married was more than this.
这是布莱伍德大人的辩词
It is Lord Blackwood's contention, therefore,
他说是布拉肯家族趁着夜色
that the Brackens moved the boundary stones
挪动了界石
in the dead of the night
还把马放养在他的领地上吃草
and put their horses to graze in his field.
那这事怎么不跟葛拉佛大人去讲？
Why was this issue not brought before Lord Grover?
他已经虚弱到连为了块石头争吵这种事都摆不平了吗？
Has he grown so feeble he cannot settle a quarrel over rocks?
我听说葛拉佛大人之子已经是奔流城有实无名的主人了
I've heard tale that Lord Grover's son now rules Riverrun in all but name.
那他也是徒利家的人 就该管好徒利家的事
Well, he is also a Tully and this remains a Tully problem.
欧维尔
大学士
我赞同
I would agree.
林曼·毕斯柏里
财政大臣
泰兰·兰尼斯特
杰森的双胞胎弟弟 海政大臣
- 能进行下一个话题了吗 大人们 - 反正吧
-If we may move on, my lords-- -And yet,
布雷肯家族和布莱伍德家族
the Brackens and the Blackwoods
贾斯皮·威尔德
法务大臣
随便什么理由都能跟对方争个你死我活
will use any excuse to spill each other's blood.
所以这桩纠纷值得调查
So this dispute bears looking into.
肯定能找到了解实情的农民
There will be countryfolk who know
知道祖辈是怎么划分地界的
where the lines have been drawn for generations.
这是好办法
That is easy enough.
说得是呢
Of course.
泰兰大人
Ser Tyland.
我们需要处理
We should address
石阶列岛的最新局势 大人们
the latest developments in the Stepstones, my lords.
那地方的破事什么时候是个头？
Will we ever be shut of that blasted place?
要我说呢 是布莱伍德家
If you ask me, I think the Blackwoods have
在这件事上更占理
the upper hand.
服了
No.
我们已经在说石阶列岛的问题了 毕斯柏里大人
We've moved on to the Stepstones, Lord Beesbury.
三女儿王国和多恩缔结了新的联盟
And the Triarchy's new alliance with Dorne.
我原本希望咱们和阳戟城的沟通
I was hoping our negotiations with Sunspear
可以劝服多恩人理智行动
might persuade them to see reason.
指望马泰尔家族 必然会失望
To trust a Martell is to be disappointed.
而且我很好奇 咱们的戴蒙王子去哪了？
And where, I wonder, is our Prince Daemon?
还是我该按他自封的头衔叫他戴蒙王呢
Or I suppose I should call him King, as he styled himself
当时他在那里打赢了一场仗 就那一次
when he won a battle there... once.
那是十年前的事了 此后他就留着那里毫不设防
That was a decade ago and he has since left the region undefended.
是我们留着那里毫不设防
We have left it undefended.
我们本该修筑防御工事
There should've been fortifications built,
望塔 舰队
watchtowers, a fleet of ships,
还有驻守士兵 才能守住它
a garrison of soldiers sent to hold our ground.
我们负担不起
We cannot afford it.
国库是很大 但终有上限
Our coffers are great, but not infinite.
我们必须考虑臣民付出的代价
We must consider the cost to our subjects.
- 我非常赞同 - 战争的代价更大
-I must agree. -The cost of war is greater.
但我们一直忽视 现在过去的怪兽又冒头了
But we have been lax and the old monster now lifts its head.
今天就到此为止吧
Let us be finished.
是
Yes.
等下
Wait.
我有话想说
I wish to speak.
大家就坐
Be seated.
我注意到……
I have felt the...
我们两家……
strife...
最近有一些不合 王后陛下
between our families of late, my Queen.
如果我方对您的家人有什么冒犯 我向您道歉
And for any offense given by mine, I apologize.
但我们本来是一家人
But we are one house.
更早之前
And long before that,
我们还曾是密友
we were friends.
我的儿子杰卡里斯会从我这里继承铁王座
My son Jacaerys will inherit the Iron Throne after me.
因此我提议让他和您的女儿海伦娜订亲
I propose we betroth him to your daughter, Helaena.
彼此结盟……
Ally ourselves...
永固统治
once and for all.
让他们一道统治吧
Let them rule together.
非常明智的提议
A most judicious proposition.
另外 如果叙拉克丝还能再产一窝龙蛋
Additionally, if Syrax brings forth another clutch of eggs,
您的儿子伊蒙德可以从中自行挑选
your son Aemond will have his choice of them...
以示我方的友善
a symbol of our goodwill.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
啊七层地狱啊 呃
Oh, Seven Hells. Um.
好女儿……
My dear...
龙蛋是件慷慨的赠礼
a dragon's egg is a handsome gift.
国王和我感谢你的提议 我们会认真考虑的
The King and I thank you for your offer and we will consider it duly.
你该休息了 夫君
You must rest now, husband.
好吧
Yes.
狐狸被猎狗追到墙角时自然会甜言蜜语
How sweetly the fox speaks when it's been cornered by the hounds.
- 她是真心的 - 她是真急了
-She is sincere. -She is desperate.
觉得自己的立足之地越来越小
She feels the earth washing away beneath her feet
现在居然指望我们无视她的过错
and now she expects us to ignore her transgressions
让我把唯一的女儿嫁给她那……
and for me to marry my only daughter to one of her...
相貌平平的儿子
plain-featured sons.
这个提议很好 我的王后
The proposal is a good one, my Queen.
我们是一家人
We're a family.
就不要孩子气地争吵下去了
Let us put aside these childish quarrels.
联手才能更加强势
Join hands and be stronger for it.
那就如您所愿吧 夫君……
You may do as you wish, husband...
等我在坟墓里凉透了 您就自行安排
when I am cold in my grave.
阿莉森
Alicent.
阿莉森！
Alicent!
不用给我盖毯子——
I do not need the blanket--
首相求见 陛下
The Hand, Your Grace.
- 国王要休息 - 我可以见他
-The King is resting. -I will see him.
坐起来点
Lean forward.
烦心事真是一个接一个啊 莱昂诺
I'm being endlessly fussed over, Lyonel.
没人来厕所找我 真是奇迹
It's a wonder I can visit the privy alone.
抱歉 陛下
Your Grace.
你过来又是有什么事 莱昂诺大人？
What might this errand be about, Lord Lyonel?
陛下 我认为……
Your Grace, I feel...
我是来向您请辞国王之手一职的
I have come to resign my position as Hand of the King.
今早院子里的插曲
The episode in the yard this morning.
犬子哈尔温实在有失体面
My son Harwin has disgraced himself
用不了多久君临所有渔妇就都要嚼舌根了
and every fishwife in King's Landing will soon be telling the tale.
确实 年轻的哈尔温这般发火很不得体
Young Harwin's outburst was unfortunate, it's true.
但他已经被都城守备队开除
But he's been expelled from the City Watch.
这个处罚已经足够了吧
That seems punishment enough.
无意冒犯 陛下 但并不足够
Forgive me, Your Grace, it is not.
你是我多年的忠臣
You have served me faithfully for many years,
首相也当了十年了
10 as Hand.
你的意见一直明智无私
Your advice has been sage, unmarked by self-interest...
可谓鹤立鸡群
which stands in contrast to all others.
陛下过奖了……
You speak kind words...
但现在阴影笼罩着我的家族
but there is a shadow over my house
并且日渐昏暗
and it grows ever darker.
我无法再正直地侍奉您
I can no longer serve you with integrity.
什么阴影？
What is this shadow?
如果它投下了这么深的阴影 那就明说吧
Name it, if it casts such a gloom.
没错 我们必须听您明明白白地说出缘由
Yes, we must have your reasoning in plain language.
我不能说
I cannot.
那我就不能同意你辞职
Then I cannot accept this.
- 亲爱的丈夫—— - 我说了不行！
- My dear husband-- - I said no!
- 如果您坚持的话 国王陛下 - 我坚持
- If you insist, my King. - I do.
你将继续侍奉国王
You will continue in your service to the crown.
那我请求暂时离开 把我的儿子从宫中带走
I would then ask leave to take my son from court
护送他回到赫伦堡的家里
and escort him back to the family seat at Harrenhal.
他是我的继承人
He is my heir
有朝一日也将成为赫伦堡伯爵
and will be lord of Harren's castle one day.
是时候让他担起这份责任了
It is time he assumed his duties there.
去吧
Do it.
你不打算帮我一下吗？
Aren't you gonna help me?
拉里斯·斯壮
“弯足” 莱昂诺的次子
王后陛下 我先擅自开始了 没有等您
I took the liberty of beginning without you, Your Grace.
让这么美味的派冷掉似乎是一种罪
It seemed a sin to let such a pie grow cold.
明智的做法 拉里斯大人
You did wisely, Lord Larys.
不过你肯定没这么担心过酒
Though you had no such worry about the wine, surely.
吃肉不喝酒也是一种罪
Meat without wine is also a sin.
把红堡中发生的一切告知您是我的责任
It's been my duty to tell you of happenings about the castle,
不过今晚的事您先知道了 我还不知道
but tonight you know, and I do not.
国王面见了我的父亲
The King had an audience with my father.
他试图辞去职务
He attempted to resign his post.
我想也是
I thought as much.
他那荣誉感一直是挂在他高贵脖颈上的重担
His honor's always been a millstone about his esteemed neck.
有意思的是 您说他“试图”辞职？
Interesting you said "attempted"?
我的国王夫君拒绝接受
My lord husband refused to accept.
那看来他没能坦白我哥哥的……失德
Then he fell short of confessing my brother's... transgressions.
你哥哥在院子里的情绪爆发
With his eruption in the yard, your brother
就已经供认了事情的真相
all but confessed the truth himself.
真相的滋味可不止一种 王后陛下
Truth has many flavors, Your Grace.
您难道期望着国王流放他亲爱的女儿
Do you expect the King to doom his dear daughter to exile,
甚至——
or even--
塔雅 现在不是时候
Talya, not now.
这是国王执拗的盲目
It's a willful blindness, the King.
我想 您肯定也有同样的苦恼
I mean, you'd surely suffer the same affliction,
- 如果碰到这种情况  - 我不会
- if it came to it. - I would not.
莱昂诺大人即将护送哈尔温爵士返回赫伦堡
Lord Lyonel is to escort Ser Harwin back to Harrenhal
监管自己的族堡 同时继续担任首相
to watch over his seat whilst he continues to serve as Hand.
但是首相已经被他儿子的行为危害
But the Hand is compromised by the acts of his son.
我父亲已经无法向国王给出不偏不倚的建议
My father cannot give unbiased counsel to the King.
就是现在这种时候让我最愤恨我父亲不在这里
It is now that I most rue the absence of my own father.
他会毫不犹豫地告诉国王真相
He wouldn't hesitate to speak the truth to the King.
假如奥托·海塔尔还是首相——
If Otto Hightower were still Hand--
王后陛下 您无法确定您的父亲
You cannot say, my Queen, that your father would be
在这件事上会不偏不倚
impartial in this matter.
不 但他会偏向我！
No, but he would be partial to me!
整个君临城里 就没有人站在我这边吗？
In all of King's Landing, is there no one to take my side?
我面前这是一群大英雄啊
What a collection of heroes I have before me.
一个杀人犯……
A murderer...
一个变态……
a deviant...
还有一个王国的叛徒
a traitor to the crown.
犯了这些罪 你们已经被判了绞刑
For your crimes, you've been sentenced to death by hanging.
你想要我们怎样？
What do you want with us?
我打算给你们仁慈……
I am prepared to offer you mercy...
如果你们愿意付出一点代价的话
if you're prepared to pay a little price.
用力 夫人
Push, my Lady.
用力！用力！
Push! Push!
用力！
Push!
- 您一定要用力！ - 用力！
- You must push! - Push!
必须现在就出来！
It needs to come now!
用力！
Push!
您现在必须用力 夫人！
You must push now, my Lady!
用力！
Push!
我已经尽我所能了
I've reached the limit of my art.
孩子还是出不来
The child will not come.
我勇敢的女孩啊
My brave girl.
我很抱歉 王子殿下
I am very sorry, my Prince.
我们还可以试着用刀……
We could lay open the womb...
打开子宫
try to remove the infant
取出婴儿
by way of the blade.
但我无法保证它能活下来
But I cannot say for a surety whether it lives.
母亲能活下来吗？
Would the mother survive it?
不能
No.
瓦格哈尔 龙焰
Vhagar, dracarys.
龙焰！
Dracarys!
龙焰
Dracarys.
龙焰！
Dracarys!
龙焰
Dracarys.
兰娜尔！
Laena!
对你们的母亲好一些 小子们
Be good to your mother, lads.
我有空就去看你们
I'll visit when I can.
不过可能得过些日子了
But that may be some time.
小杰
Jace.
我会回来的……
I will return...
我保证
I promise.
再见面时 我就是个陌生人了
I will be a stranger when we meet again.
公主殿下
Princess.
我们可以用渡鸦传书
We will exchange letters by raven.
- 是不是很有意思？ - 哈尔温·斯壮是我父亲吗？
- Won't that be fun? - Is Harwin Strong my father?
我是私生子吗？
Am I a bastard?
你是坦格利安族人
You are a Targaryen.
这才是唯一重要的事
That's all that matters.
借一步说话？
A word?
看来他已经走了
I take it he's gone.
我们不在这里待了 准备走吧
We're finished here. We're leaving.
那你的提议呢？小杰和海伦娜的事？
What of your offer? Jace and Helaena?
我的形象已经被破坏了……
I have been undermined...
我已经成了笑话 他们都在走廊里议论我
and made a spectacle. They whisper about me in the corridors.
那好 随他们吧
Well, I leave them to it.
那 回龙石岛吗？
To Dragonstone then?
我们早就该离开了
We should've left years ago.
你的位子怎么办？
What of your position?
你一直说如果你不在宫中
You've always said if you were absent from court,
她就会在你父亲耳边进尽谗言
she would pour her honey in your father's ear.
明智的水手会趁风暴汇聚的时候逃走
The wise sailor flees the storm as it gathers.
兰尼诺……
Laenor...
带上他吧
bring him.
我们需要每一把能使唤的剑
We'll need every sword we can muster.
着火了！我要烧死了！
Fire! I will burn!
哈尔温！哈尔温！
Harwin! Harwin!
[拉里斯·斯壮] 除了成为弱点 子嗣还能是什么？
What are children, but a weakness?
愚行？
A folly?
徒劳？
A futility?
通过子女 你幻想着骗过注定胜利的大黑暗
Through them, you imagine you cheat the great darkness of its victory.
你会永远以某种形式存在下去
You will persist forever, in some form or another.
就好似子女会防止你化作尘土
As if they will keep you from the dust.
但为了他们 你会交出本不该放弃的东西
But for them, you surrender what you should not.
或许你知道怎样做是对的
You may know what is the right thing to be done,
但爱总能占据上风
but love stays the hand.
爱……
Love...
就是失败的原因
is a downfall.
要我说的话……最好让你的人生
Best to make your way through life unencumbered...
没有牵绊
if you ask me.
他们死了
They're dead.
您一定听说过赫伦堡的故事吧 陛下
You've heard the stories of Harrenhal, Your Grace.
它以黑心赫伦的傲慢筑就
It was built in hubris by Harren the Black
用以纪念他自己的伟大
as a monument to his own greatness.
筑城的泥灰中混杂着鲜血
Blood mixed into the mortar.
据说赫伦堡受到了诅咒
It is said to be a cursed place.
它会审判每一个从大门通过的人
That it passes judgment on all who pass beneath its gates.
是你——
You--
作出审判的是你
You passed judgment.
王后许下了愿望
The Queen makes a wish.
王国的哪个仆人不会尽力实现它呢？
What servant of the realm would not strive to fulfill it?
我想您现在会给您的父亲写信了吧？
I assume you will write to your father now?
拉里斯……
Larys...
我没想把事情搞成这样
I did not wish for this.
我很肯定 等时机成熟了……
I feel certain you will reward me...
您会奖赏我的
when the time is right.